<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some remarks upon a scandalous libel, intituled, The declaration of James Duke of Monmouth, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93529</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4604B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184454</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43078154</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43078154</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151739</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93529)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2274:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some remarks upon a scandalous libel, intituled, The declaration of James Duke of Monmouth, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Publication information suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monmouth, James Scott, --  Duke of, 1649-1685.</term>
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Monmouth's Rebellion, 1685 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151739:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Some Remarks Upon a Scandalous LIBEL, Intituled <hi>The Declaration of James, Duke of Monmouth, &amp;c,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving lately peruſed a printed Paper, intituled <hi>The Declaration of James, Duke of Monmouth, &amp;c.</hi> I thought it my duty as a true ſubject of England, a true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, an honeſt man, and a lover of truth, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge (as far as in my Power it lyes) All true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, true Proteſtants and honeſt men from the Imputation of being any ways concern'd in abeting ſoe villanous a Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Next, I ſhall endeavour to vindicate His preſent Majeſtie and Parliament under Hîm aſſembled, together with thoſe ſubordinate Gouvernours, Inſinuated, or intended in the ſaid Declaration, from any irregular proceeding in their adminiſtration of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, I ſhall anſwer ſuch particular accuſations as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the ſaid Declaration, have falſly and impudently laid upon His Maj. (or any under Him) as they concerne his own Royal Perſon, the Proteſtant Religion ' or our own lives, liberties, or Properties.</p>
            <p>To the firſt, I doe affirme that all the true Subjects, true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and honeſt men within the Kingdome of England, have promiſ'd and ſworne to oppoſe to the utmoſt of their power with theire lives and fortunes, <hi>All ſuch Noblemen, Gentlemen and Others now in Armes,</hi> who will own, or are ſuppoſed to have ſigned, agreed to, or are meant to be Included in the ſaid Traiterous Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151739:2"/>
To prove this, I referre the Readers to the Oaths of <hi>Alleageance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> generally taken by all Subjects, as alſo the ſeveral ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes of all the Counties, Shires and Corporations within the Kingdome of England; but more particularly to the late unanimous Addreſſe and votes of Both Houſes of Parl. about the 23, of <hi>May</hi> laſt as alſo of <hi>June 13th. That they would aſſiſt His Majeſtie with theire lives and fortunes againſt</hi> Argyle, <hi>and</hi> James, <hi>Duke of</hi> Monmouth, <hi>and there Adherants, and all Rebels and Traitors and All Others whatſoever that shall aſſiſt them or any of them.</hi> And when I come to ſpeake of Parl. I ſhall make it evidently appeare, that this preſent Parl. is the true, legal, and only Repreſentative of all the Subects of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. And I doubt not but our neighbour Nations are already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinct, That the Kingdoms of <hi>Great Brittaine</hi> deteſt and abhorre this ſaid traiterous Declaration, and all Perſons abetting or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing it.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond: The ſaid Declaration ſetts forth that <hi>His preſent Majeſtie uſurped the Crowne.</hi> That he <hi>avows Himſelfe to be of the Romish Religion;</hi> That he <hi>hath cald in multitudes of Priefts and Jeſuits.</hi> That he <hi>hath govern'd arbitrarily by collecting the Cuſtoms and Exciſe ſence the death of the late King.</hi> That his <hi>Judges are ſuborned and fors worne.</hi> That the <hi>preſent Parl. is packt by falſe returns, Illegal Chartres, with a great</hi> deal more of ſuch ſtuffe, which oblidg'd them to <hi>be take them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selus to Arms.</hi> Theſe accuſations help to make up ſoe abſurd and ridiculous a libel, that it wants the Common Excuſe of pleſantrie and witt, and indeed deſerv's nor a ſober anſwer. But, leaſt ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſhould poſſibly be impoſ'd upon for want of that true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Engliſh affairs and Government, which Engliſhmen are ſuppoſ'd to have, I ſhall bieifly anſwer every particutar Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, His Majeſties right to the Crowne is ſo evident and cleare, that I chalenge all Hiſtorians, Civil Lawers or Examples in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome to ſett forth a Title in an Hereditary Kingdome freer from Uſurpation then His own, both as to matter of Law, and matter of fact. For (ſuppoſeing King Charles the 2d. dyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out legitimate Iſſue) His preſent Majeſtie is acknowledged by his Enemies as well as by all Chriſtendome, to be indubitably the next, and Immediate Heir to His Brother. His acceſſion to the Crown was ſo peaceable, that there was not ſo much as one ſword drawn, nor one ſingle man raiſ'd to promote him to it or ſupport him in it: it was in plain words reſigned and delivered to Him by His Royal Brother upon his death bed; He was as peaceably pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd and Crown'd; As peaceably acknowledged by voluntary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151739:2"/>adereſſes from all parts of His Dominions: By all forrain Princes; By the States of Hôlland and Thoſe who have there at preſent the next and moſt Immediate right to ſucceed after Him, and even by Amſterdam it ſelfe: and all this unanimouſly acknowledged and conferm'd by the two Parl. of England and Scotland and univerſal Concurrance of Ireland. All this would be ſo plain that the moſt ignorant might comprehend it, were it not that <hi>James, Duke of Monmouth hath been and ſtill is believed to have a legitimate and legal right to the Crown of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, with the Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions thereunto belonging:</hi> In anſwer to this, I doe affirme, that were the ſaid Noble Dukes right to the Crowns of England &amp;c. <hi>legitimate</hi> and <hi>legal</hi> as he pretends, yet as his circumſtances have hitherto ſtood, <hi>His preſent Majeſtie is noe Uſurper.</hi> To prove this further, I muſt acquaint thoſe who have not heard it (if any ſuch there be) that the ſaid Duke was not only never ownd by the King, Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, or any Parl. which hath ever ſett ſence the late Kings happy reſtoration, But he hath been as publickly, ſolemly and legally diſclaim'd and diſown'd to be the Kings legitimate ſon by them All, as poſſibly the nature of the caſe would admittt: He as thankfully himſelfe accepted the honour of bring declared the Kings Natural Son, when from Mr James Croftes (the reputed ſon of the late Lord Crofts) he was by the mere favour and goodneſſe and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of His preſent Majeſtie prefer'd to that, and thoſe high Titles which he lately enjoyd: And the late King himſelfe, when he was upon his death bed, and ſenſible that he could not out live 24. hours, and by conſequence had noe apprchenſions of <hi>popish poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> or <hi>blunderbeſses,</hi> or could be influenced by <hi>Popish Motives</hi> or <hi>Inſtigations,</hi> was ſo fair from declaring him His legitimate Son, or leaving his Crown unto him; That he left him not ſoe much as his bleſſing, which indeed he had obſtinately forſeited by being a treble traitor, to his King, his Country, and to his Father, and by giving publickly the lye, to his late and preſent Majeſtie, by that Gentleman like trick with which he took his laſt leave of white hall. Now when theſe known circumſtances (beſides many more too long to be ſett forth) ſhall be duly conſidered, let all ſober and Impartial men judge, whether there be the leaſt probable grounds to believe this pretended <hi>legitimate</hi> and <hi>legal right,</hi> and whether it be morally poſſible, that the King ſhould be ſoe unjuſt and unnatural, as to diſinherit his only Son, Whom he ſo long, and ſo truly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and moreover ſhould confirme it too, even at laſt, when neither hopes nor danger could prevent Him from declaring the truth: The pretended right therefore of the Duke of Monmouth,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151739:3"/>being ſo highly improbable, or at leaſt, doubtful, I ſay in this caſe, altho the Duke of Monmouth had a concealed right, yet in the mean time until this right could be legally and peaceably prov'd and granted to him, His preſent Majeſtie cannot be reputed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reaſon, in Law, or in conſcience an <hi>Uſurper.</hi> This accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore is (as I ſaid) ridiculous and frivolous. His Majeſties next pretended crime is, <hi>that he ownd Himſelf bairfac't to be of the Romish Religion.</hi> Indeed it ſeems ſtrange, that the Son of a King, and pretended Heir to three Kingdoms: Should have yet to lettle ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in him, as to impute it a crime to a Prince to practiſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly the Religion which he profeſſeth. Muſt Hypocricie be the badge of reformation? And muſt Integritie and ſinceritie be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed criminal by the pretended reſtorer of the truwe Chriſtian faith? Ah James Scott, God who is the Searcher of hearts, knows how well thy principles and thy practiſes agree; And I muſt ſay (for I am noe flatterer) 'tis to be believed that were your inward man as truly known as your outward man hath been (notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe ſeveral ſhapes through which it hath lately run) the r's not a Turk but would be aſhamd to accept of thee for a partner much more a <hi>Protector</hi> of his faith. Thirdly we are told that His Majeſtie <hi>Hath cald over multitudes of Prieſes and Jeſuites.</hi> Suppoſeing this were true, I can ſcarce tell of what nature his fault would be; But this I certainly know, that the indiſcretion of thoſe multitudes who went over, Isun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonnable, ſince they know how they are expoſed and lvable not only to impriſonements, but even to the ſentences of death it ſelfe; And for once I will advance a Negative againſt a ſingle affirmative, and ſay (upon much better grounds then they affirme) that His Majeſtie hath never cald in ſuch multitudes of Prieſts and Jeſuites as is pretended, but on the contrary I have good reaſon to believe that he doth totally diſcountenance all ſuch, except thoſe few who may be employed for the ſervice of His own Chappel. 4tlv It is objected, That His Majeſtie hath <hi>govern'd arbitrarily by collecting the Cuſtoms and Exciſe ſence the death of the late King:</hi> Alas Gentlemen, doth all this noiſe and up roar againſt Arbitrary Power, abſolute Tyranny &amp;c. conclude in this one ſingle pretended Inſtance of it? The caſe then is this: The Parl. of England had granted to the late King (upon good cauſes and confiderations the fornamed Cuſtoms and Exciſe during His life: The King dyes, and His preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie by Proclamation with the advice of His Privy Councel, orders the Collection of the ſame until the meeting of the next Parl: Some reaſons I have heard given; and they were theſe, Firſt, becauſe theſe Cuſtoms and Exciſe being granted to the late King towards
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151739:3"/>the Support of the nauye, and for the defence of the Kingdom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt its Enemies, if the effect be neceſſary, the cauſe muſt equally continue and the defence of the Kingdome, being the ſafety of the people which is the <hi>Suprema Lex,</hi> the <hi>means</hi> to procure this ſafety is always ſuppoſed to be alſo granted, for <hi>qui dat finem dat etiam media,</hi> eſpecially ſence the Cuſtoms ſo collected, were to continue no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then untill ſuch time as a Parl. could conueniently Aſſemble; Beſides, the Merchants themſelves agreed generally to the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theſe Cuſtoms, and declard, that (without any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the King in the caſe) the abrupt ſtopping of the ſaid Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, would prove more prejudicial to the Merchants univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then the payment of them could poſſibly be. Thirdly, the collection of theſe ſaid Cuſtoms was not only reaſonable and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but in the Opinion of eight of the twelve Judges (as theſe noble declaring Gentlemen confeſſe) it was alſo Judged legal, and according to the conſtant Cuſtome and ancient practice in ſuch like caſes. And laſtly, the Parl. being Aſſembled, was ſo far from calling the Judges to account for their Judgement, or the officers for their collection, that they immediately confirmd the ſame to His preſent Majeſtie as they had formerly done to the late King. Now let the world Judge what reaſon theſe violent men have to take up Arms, againſt their lawful King and Governor (which neither reaſon nor religion could ever Juſtifie) upon the pretence of arbitrary power and Tyranny, when this caſe of collercting the Cuſtoms, reſolved by the Judges as a foreſaid, is the only ſingle Inſtance which they have produict for either: <hi>men and Brethren exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your ſelves for yee know not what Spirit yee are of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to obuiate and preclude my anſwer to the aforeſaid caſe of the Cuſtoms, theſe Gentlemen have branded our Judges with the Infamous Titles <hi>of ſubornd</hi> and <hi>foreſworn:</hi> In deed I know not how farr theſe reverend Judges of the Land, and adminiſtrators of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice amongſt us (made alſo by the late King) may be guilty of two ſuch crimes as perjurye and ſubornation, but this I will affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, that if ſo many men born of good families, of honourable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, learning, wiſdome, pietie, and of irreprochable lives and converſations can be capable of committing ſuch enormous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, I can never reaſonably hope to ſee the Benches free from corrupt mercinary and the worſt of men, no, not when James Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of Monmouth and his Rebells shall <hi>have taken care for the future for debarring ignorant ſcandalous and mercinary men from the adminiſtration of Juſtice, and that the judges shall hold their places by the ancient tenure of quamdiu ſe bene geſſerint, or that the wiſdome of his imaginary Parl. shall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151739:4"/>have ſettled ſome way and method for the approbation of ſuch as ſhall be aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the degree and dignitie of Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, that no conſideration might ſtop the progres of their villanous deſignes, and having made way for the execution of them by the condemnation of the King with all His Miniſters and Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they now fall foul upon, and profane their pretended ſacred I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol, Parl. and tell us that <hi>this preſent Parl. is a Company of men, pack't together by falſe retuns, illegall Chartres and other corrupt means.</hi> And ſo by the way leaves noe hopes of a true legal Parl. whilſt the ſun and moon endure; for if James Duke of York a Traitor, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and a popiſh uſurper (as they call Him) hath been able with out force to pack ſuch a Parl. in which there are as many; Rich, Noble, Honeſt worthy Gentlemen, as any Parl hath ever known how ſhall we hope that the true Proteſtant James Duke of Monmouth back't by his pretended legitimate and legal right, together with the power of the ſword ſhould not be much more able to pack a Parl. of the greateſt rebells Traitors Schiſmaticks and villains (to the deſtruction of all good men) that any age hath ever yet product The Experience of this hath been ſufficiently ſeen in the late rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, for which (with the murder of the bleſſed Martyr King Charles the firſt, his partner and accomplice Argyle, is not aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Blaſpemouſly to returne the glory to God. But to come to the meritt of the cauſe, I muſt acquaint you how the conſtitution of Parliaments hath been for nere 500 Years, which is a ſufficient ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me for our purpoſe, without ſearching farther into Antiquitie: I ſhall tell you then, that the Parliamentaire Repreſentatives of the Nation were chiefly the Barons of England, and Knights of the ſeveral Shires, &amp; Counties therein: Theſe two remaine with little or no alteration from that time to this, and to ſhow how farr the ſaid Knights may be taken at this day, for the Repreſentatives of the Common of England, I muſt alſo Informe you. That every Knicht of the ſheir; is choſen by the Major part of all ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners who wiſh in the ſaid ſhires or Counties, have the value of 40 ſh. per ann. freehold in the ſaid ſhires or Counties: Which privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge comprehends ſo great a number of Houſeholders, that there are few men excluded beſides ſervants and ſome farmers who are often times ſtrangers come in unto us: And the Election of theſe Knights of the Shires &amp; Counties remains as it anciently was, without any alteration Illegal Chartres, or any falſe returns or corrupt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans other then what might have been uſed ever ſence their firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and may continue to the end of Parls and time. Illegal Chartres then have no relation to Knights of the Shires, becauſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151739:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>there neither are, nor never were any Chartres in the caſe, and if any falſe returns have been made, or corrupt means uſed, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament it ſelf when fully Aſſembled is Judge of the right att this day, as formerly at any time it had been; Thus we ſee how far, Knights of the ſhires may be repreſentatives of the Commons of England, and where the abuſes or corrupt means in the choice of them, are to be Judg'd and rectifyed.</p>
            <p>The accuſation then of Illegal Chartres is applicable to Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations only, which from the Kings Chartres or Grants have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Priviledge of ſending Burgeſſes or Parl. men to Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; To explain this, I doe again affirme (and I chalenge all the complotters of this Rebellious Declaration to ſhow the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) that this priviledge of Corporations began not untill the time of King John who reigned about the year of our Lord 1199. Which was nere 140. Yeares after William the Conqueror and who was the founder of many and cald the Patron of all Corporations: The Occaſion in ſhort was this: King John, to Ballance the Power of his rebellious Barons erected ſeverall Corporations, and out of his meer favour and benevolence, granted Chartres to them upon ſeverall Conditons and limitations, by which they had the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of chooſing and ſending Burgeſſes to Parl. From hence we muſt obſerve theſe things. 1<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi>. that this Priviledge of Corporations was noe ancienter then the time of King John, and by conſequence not a fundamentall part of the Engliſh Monarchie, which was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent ſo it and the Creator of it 2. This priviledge ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the meer grace and benevolence of our Monarchs, and laſtly that it was granted upon ſeverall conditions, which when bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, their Chartres were forfaited in Law, and their Priviledges cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: And accordingly during this intervall of time, the Charters of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Corporations, even that of London it ſelfe) were forfeited ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, and ſome times taken away. This then being the true caſe of Chartres and Corporations, we muſt next obſerve That King Charles 2d. finding ſeveral corporations had notoriouſly broaken, or not performed thoſe conditions by which they held theire Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres, He cites them in a legal way by quo warranto's to trye thire Caſe at Law, whereafter a full hearing, (even to the content of the parties concern'd) with the aſſiſtance of the moſt learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel that England afforded (as in the caſe of the Charter of London) the verdicts have been given for the King, and many other Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſenſible of there guilt, or deſirous to have the Conditions of their Charters altered, having ſurrend'red there old Chartres in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the late King, His ſaid Majeſtie out of his meer grace and favour. did either confirme the old Chartres, or gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151739:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>new ones with ſuch conditions and limitations, as in His Princely Wiſdome He thought moſt fitt, according to the undoubted right of King John, and the reſt of His Royal Progenitors. Now by vertue of theſe Chartres, and according to the Powers and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges therein expreſt, thoſe Corporations have choſen and ſent theire Repreſeutatives or Burgheffes to his preſent Parl. And this being the exact State of the caſe, I appeal to all men of ſence and reaſon, whether theſe Chartres can be cald Illegal, or theire Burgeſſes (being duly choſen according to them) a Company of men packt together by corrupt and fraudulent means. And this confirms what I att firſt averd, that this preſent Parl. being the true, legal and only Repreſentative of all the true Subjects of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, the whole Nation hath by them deteſted and abhord this trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Declaration and all the Rebells concerned in it.</p>
            <p>I come now to the third and laſt head which contains the falſe impudent and particular reflections of the late Duke of Moumouth againſt His Majeſties ſacred Perſon, in which he is not aſhamd like a baſe villain, to call him murderer, Aſſaſſim, Traitor and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and inſtanceth the murder of Sr <hi>Edmund Bury Godfrey,</hi> the death of the late Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and that even of the late King His moſt dearely beloved Brother. He mentions alſo the burning of the city of London, and ſubordination of falſe witneſſes; Now let all men of honout, and men of arms Judge, whether this be like a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of warr upon the pretence of a <hi>legal and legitimate right to three Kingdoms,</hi> or rather the moſt ſcurrulous and ſawcy Invective of ſome mean poor ſpirited railing fellow, who ſhows himſelfe at leaſt hereby to be the true Son of that impudent ſcandalous abandond woman his Mother, who after Monmouth was borne became a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtrumpett ſo many Perſons now alive whom I know, and could name: <hi>Hold not thy tongue o God of my praiſe, for the mouth of the wicked, and the mouthful of deceit, are opered upon me; They have ſpoken to me with a lying tongue, They compeſſed me about alſo with words of hatred, and fought againſt me without a cauſe, They have rewarded me evil for good and hatred for my friendship; let his days be few, and let another take his charge, let his poſteritie he deſtroyed, and in the generation following, let theire name bt put out, Pſal.</hi> 109.</p>
            <p>It would be impertinency and great preſumption in me ſhould I pretend to anſwer crimes, which are ſoe farr from being ſuſpected to be true, that I am perſwaded they are not believed by the Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers themſelves: Beſides, as the truth of moſt of theſe caſes hath been legally diſcover'd and atteſted, ſoe neither time nor place will permitt me to infert the ſeveral tryals and Evidences, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151739:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>have been given in them. I am ſufficietly convinct, That the moſt unſpotted honour, and moſt Royal, Heroick, generous and pious principles, and actions of His preſent Majeſtie, even to niceneſſe It ſelfe, through the whole courſe and circumſtances of his life, and ſeries of His private as well as publick actions, are ſoe notoriouſly known through the whole world, that all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, with the Kings and Princes thereof, would unanimouſly concur, and beg to become His Compurgators, and from theire ſouls abhorr and deteſt thoſe moſt villanous men, and worſt of Traitors, who ſoe falſly, maliciouſly and ſawcily have dar'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane the Sacred Caracter of ſoe Incomparable a Prince: but that I may undeceive ſome Innocent men and ſtrangers to Our Country who it may be have been poyſned by the falſe reports, falſe Oaths and perjuries of theſe profligate, out lawd, and inſolent Traitors; I muſt humbly beg His Majeſties leave, that I may ſpeak to two of thoſe particulars, of which being my ſelf an eye witneſſe to the one, and a competent, and Impartial Judge of the other, I perſwade my ſelfe, that according to the truth of theſe two caſes, Thoſe who ſhall peruſe theſe Papers, will equally judge of the reſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt is that of the burning of London: The beginning of that fire, with its growth and progres is now as generally known, as its end: I ſhall only their fore ſay this: That being my ſelfe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent moſt part of the time, both by day and by night, and a ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in that fire as well as my neighbours, I had many ſeveral occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to be very nere His preſent Majeſtie, then Duke of York, and I doe teſtifie, That His diligence, care, and pains in ſtopping that dreadful fire, was almoſt equal to any particular ſufferer in it; That His compaſſion and affliction for its progres, both in words and actions, ſeemd ſoe great as if He Himſelfe had been the only Sufferer; and His advice in quenching thoſe flames ſoe preſſing, and ſoe reaſonable, that, had not mens fears outrun theire dang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers or had His advice been vigorouſly followed, in all moral pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie, they had put a much earlier ſtop to that vaſt conflagrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and all honeſt men are throughly and fully convinct, that His then Royal high: the Duke of York, did no more directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly contrive (as they call it) the burning of the City of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, then of the ſoe much celebrated Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> (ſoe many thouſand of yeares ſence) at Epheſus.</p>
            <p>The ſecond caſe, Is the <hi>poyſning His Majeſtie</hi> of bleſſ'd memorie; Indeed the horror of ſoe damd and falſe an accuſation, with the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious inveterate malice of Jams Scott late Monmouth, and his moſt accurſed aſſociates, doth almoſt confound my thoughts, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151739:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtop my pen: However, I muſt ſay in general: That had it pleaſ'd God Almighty in his great mercy to us, to have ſent an Angel from heaven and aſſured us, that he would take (in his due time) His late Majeſtie from us, but by a death ſoe natural, that there ſhould not be the leaſt circumſtantialt conjecture of violence, I dare be bold to affirme that the witt of man could not have found out or deſired a kind of death more natural and free from the ſuſpicions of humane malice, then that of the late King. In particular, the manner of the Kings being taken with the firſt fitt, was <hi>Apoplectical,</hi> the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, <hi>Apoplectical</hi> the Method and cure of his firſt fitt by Cupping, Scarifying and ſuchlike, (accordng to the rules of art in thoſe caſes) anſwerd <hi>Apoplectical indications,</hi> the lettle diſtortion of this Mouth, and failing in His ſpeech <hi>Apoplectical,</hi> every circumſtance ſoe much Apoplectical, that His laſt fitt was plainly and truly for told Him (according to the Nature of ſuch <hi>Apoplexies</hi>) many hours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their was any outward appearance of the fitt, His Body when opend, His gutts, vitals, brains and All, were ſoe farr from ſhowing the leaſt ſuſpicion of poyſon, that they ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declared an <hi>Apoplexie,</hi> the unanimous concurrance of all his Phiſitians pronounc't a <hi>natural death:</hi> And were all theſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, with many more, inſufficient to prouve the ſame, yet the ſoft &amp; hearthy tears alone of that <hi>Undaunted Hero King James the ſecond,</hi> would convince Opinias trite and incrudulite it ſelfe, thatt was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible He ſhould with ſoe much ſorrow lamant a Death, which (as they urge) He not only had deſird but contrived, whilſt the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie of the braveſt of men, muſt have exceeded the vile diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling art of the moſt mercinary ſlave: And I defye Brinvillers (were ſhe now alive) with all the art of Indian or Siciliane Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners to invent a doſe which ſhould ſoe fully in all points &amp; Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances reſemble ſuch a natural <hi>Apoplexie,</hi> as that which caried off our late Bleſſed Soveraigne, I have only one objection to anſwer, which, how frivolous ſoever it be, yet ſince it is particular, and believed by ſome men, I beg leave to ſpeak to it: they ſay then that when the late King perceved he was poyſned, he ſhould with great paſſion utter theſe words, <hi>Good Lord, what have they done unto me?</hi> Now as ſome circumſtantial truths have been ever mingled with material falſhood, like leafe gold over bitter pills, to make them paſſe the better, ſoe I muſt ingenioſluy confeſſe, that I have heard His Majeſtie ſhould have ſpoken ſome ſuch words as thoſe, but good God, upon how different an occaſion from what it is now applyed, I have been credibbly then told, that after the King was recouvered from his firſt fitt, in which his Chyrurgeons, had cupt Him ſacrifyed and cutt him upon the ſhoulders, and other parts
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151739:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the King (not knowing what had paſt whilſt He was ſenceleſſe, (and feeling at laſt the ſmart and pain of thoſe wounds which in His fitt he had received being ſurpriſed at what he had not felt before, ſhould ſay ſome ſuch words as thoſe <hi>Good Lord, what have they done unto me?</hi> Thus we ſee Innocencye brought to ſupport the fowleſt malice, and truth it ſelfe enjag'd to confirme the moſt accurſed lye: Yet notwithſtanding all this, James, Duke of Monmouth declares he will <hi>proſecute</hi> James Duke of York (as he calls His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſtie) <hi>for the aforeſaid villanous and unnatural crime in purſuance of a vote torevenge the Kings death</hi> (upon Papiſts he ſhoold have ſaid for ſuch was the vote) <hi>in caſe he came to an untimely end, until he hath brought Him to ſuffer what the laws adjudged to be the puniſhment of ſoe execrable a fact and in a particular manner being deeply ſenſible of that barbarous and horrid parricide committed upon his father doth reſolve to perſue the ſaid James Duke of York, as a mortall and bloody Enemie, and will endeavour as well by his own hand as by the aſſiſtance of his friends and the law to have Juſtice executed upon him.</hi> Gently gently yong man and put not your ſelfe into paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, dog days are coming on, and if you heat your blood too much phlebo to my in the Jugular veyne will prove your only cure. But to be ſerious: Never was villanous cauſe ſupported by a more ſutable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, one of the moſt glorious Princes and worthieſt of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, muſt be hectord thus, and ſuffer (if they could compaſſe it) for an Imaginary crime, which was never committed by any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, beſides themſelves in their Impudent Declaration, and that in purſuance too of a vote for ſcandalous, ſoe unreaſonable and unjuſt that it muſt remaine a blott to all Parliaments and publik Aſſemblies which time it ſelfe can never wipe off. I have ſpoke what is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient concerning the death of the late King, and ſhall only give you the cauſe and motive of that noble vote:</p>
            <p>Whilſt the late popiſh plott (ſupported by the Teſtimonies of that moſt execrable perjurd villaiu Titus Oates. And ſome others as infamous as himſelfe) was moſt in vogue. The houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, out of a furious zeal to preſerve the Proteſtant Religion, had almoſt forgott Chriſtianitie, and raſhly paſt a vote, <hi>that if the late King should come to an untime end they would revenge, His death upon the</hi> Papiſts. This, how unjuſt ſoever it was, ſeemed yet tender and kind towards the late King; But oh the malice of thoſe curſed heads, who, (having impoſd upon, and deceived ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, of that miſtaken Parliament) had formd a Plott ſoe helliſh and ſoe bloody, that nothing but the barbarous in humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of it, ever made the truth of it ſuſpected: However it being
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151739:7"/>(by Gods great mercy and providence who is the Protector of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence) not only diſcoverd and prevented, but made ſoe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly plain that the whole nation is fully ſatisfyed of its truth; I ſhall acquaint you with the caſe. That <hi>voting</hi> Parl: being diſſolvd, the heads nevertheleſſe and promoters of the plott mett in Caballs, as was legally and fully examined and proved, where at laſt a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution was taken (as at firſt deſigned) that the late King ſhould be aſs aſſinated by theirs own accomplices Rumbold, Walcup and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and immediately the odium and puniſhment of theire own horrid crime, was to be Throwne and executed, not only upon all Papiſts, but upon their <hi>Bratt Prelacy,</hi> as Argile terms the Church of England; ſoe with one moſt monſtrous bloody Regedical ſtroake, they intended to have ſubverted the Government, and extirpated root and branch all thoſe who had been ever faithfull and loval to the King and our ancient Monarchie, or true ſons of the Church of England, And the pious <hi>double Apoſtate</hi> head and Capt. Generall of the Proteſtant forces (as Monmouth ſtiles himſelfe) together and in company with the ſaid Rumbold and others, the intended mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of his deare Father King Charls 2. is now deſperately, and openly endeavouring to accompliſh that curſed deſigne, which (by the eſpeciall providence of God) wanted then its damnable effect: Now if All this, and every particular of it be not true, then not only our own nation, but all the Chriſtian Princes of Europe are miſerably deceived, who ſent theire Miniſters to congratulate the the Kings happy deliverie from thoſe bloody villains, and traitors; The adreſſes to the ſame effect from all the Courties, Shires and Corporations in England, meer deluſion and mockerie; Witneſſes of their own faction, and all concurring circumſtances, meer eheat and leger demain, the Judges of our Land, deaf and blind; and the moſt legall tryalls in open Court by 12. ſubſtantiall Gentlemen and Citizens (againſt whom the criminalls themſelves had noe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions) the premeditated reſolutions of violence, and injuſtice. But on the other ſide if what we have now affirmd, and every ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall part of it be true (as heaven and earth know it is) what then ſhall we ſay to theſe incorrigible diſſembling traitors and moſt bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy minded Rebells? Heare all yee people, hearken thou O earth, and all that therein is, And let the Lord God be wittneſſe againſt you, even the Lord from his holy Temple. Mich. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> v. 2.</p>
            <p>For St Edmund bury Godfry, and the Earl of Eſſex their caſe was examined with all the ſtrictneſſe and Juſtice, that poſſibly the Law in ſuch caſes doth, or can afford, and the devil himſelfe could not have invented greater lyes; then have been publiſhed concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151739:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the latter, by ſome of the rebells, but to ſpeak more particular to that would require a larger volume. Sydney, Ruſſell and thoſe other Traitors, who were executed for theire treaſons, had not only all imaginable Juſtice, but much more favour and mercy ſhown them, then any of thoſe Papiſts who before had ſufferd. <hi>Armſtrong</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was not permitted to plead to the meritt of his crimes, not that there wanted either treaſons or wittneſſes to have hangd him ten ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes over (as was publickly offerd in the Court) but he being befor out lawed for treaſons, by due courſe of Law and not appearing or or ſunendring himſelfe <hi>voluntarily</hi> with in the time prefixt, he could noe more have the benefitt of that law from which he fled, but was ipſo facto guilty and lyable by Law to the puniſhment of treaſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept His Maj. out of his meer grace, and by the power of His Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al prerogative had pardoned his out laury and had ſet him in ſtatu quo prius; which I ſay being a meer act of mercy as that of pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a man already condemnd, it is in the Kings Royal breaſt to have mercy, on whom he will have mercy, and ſince the King was pleaſed upon this Occaſion to refuſe it, Armſtrong can noe more complain of <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> then any robber or traitor that has been executed theſe 100 Years.</p>
            <p>As for our <hi>Religion, lives, liberties</hi> and <hi>pooperties,</hi> we enjoy them with ſuch an entire, happy, lawfull freedome that we are envied by all the ſubjects of Europe; nor is there an empire, Kingdome, Commonwealth or Goverment in the whole world, under wich ſubjects may live more happy and ſecure then in our own; theſe are beſides ſoe fenced and hedged about (as the Declaration, ſayes) that I defye the witt of man, and power of Parl. to adde one word which ſhall not rather enflave then en franchiſe, ruine, then ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them. The Proteſtant Religion, as it is now profeſt, hath been ſoe eſtabliſhed and confirmed by acts of Parl. for more then theſe 100 Yeares, that except a Proteſtant Parl. (and other then ſuch there can never be) ſhould introduce poperye, and with theire our hands deliver up that power, which they doe, and may and are ſoe tenacious to preſerve, the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion muſt eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally flouriſh in England, whilſt Kings and Parliaments endure. In a word, our Religion, <hi>lives, liberties</hi> and <hi>properties</hi> an ſoe well founded, ſoe ſtrongly fortifyed, and ſoe carefully protected by Our moſt <hi>Gracious Soveraigne King James the ſecond,</hi> that with the machinations and conſpiractes of <hi>James,</hi> Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi> ſome years hence, not the preſent open hoſtilities and deteſtable Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion of James Scott, Argyl, with their Accomplices, and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance which they vainly (and injuriouſly to all Government)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151739:8"/>flatter themſelves they ſhall receive from forraine powers, will ever be able (by the bleſſing of God) ſo violate them, or break in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſpoken what is, I hope, ſufficient at leaſt what is pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually true, concerning thoſe ſeveral points of which I intended to diſcourſe: for the reſt of his inſignificant, rayling canting ſtaff. I think it not worthy of a further reply, for I perſwade my ſelfe that what hath been already ſaid, will ſatisfye al impartial Readers, but nothing will convince the poſitive and the prejudic't. His <hi>promiſes</hi> and his <hi>threats</hi> which are vaſtly great, are equally ayrie and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and this <hi>Chymerical Hero</hi> woul have done mutch better to have employed his thoughts upon ſome new conqueſt in <hi>Terra Auſirali incognita,</hi> or of the world in the moon, then thus unjuſtly, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edley, and bloodily endeavour to diſturbe the peace of three Kingdoms, which deteſt his principles and diſown his pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>For thoſe <hi>Proteſtant Kings, Princes,</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> whom he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently invites to partake with him in his rebellion, as it is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick afront, and unpardonable injurie to them all, ſoe I doubt not but they will all as publickly diſown both him, and his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants.</p>
            <p>To conclude, if ever Rebellion was grounded upon the falſeſt of pretences, <hi>it is this.</hi> If ever rebellion was raiſd by the worſt of of men, againſt the Beſt of Princes, <hi>it is this,</hi> and laſtly, if the moſt notorious, barefac't ſinns of <hi>fornication, adulterie, cold murder</hi> and <hi>repeated apoſtacies, rapes</hi> and <hi>inceſt,</hi> were loſt in the whole world beſides, they might be found in <hi>James Scott</hi> the pretended <hi>double head,</hi> and <hi>twice apoſtat popish</hi> Capt. Generall of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> forces and <hi>falſe protectors</hi> of the reformed <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Lord God the Avenger, shew thy ſelfe clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Exalt thy ſelfe. O Judge of the World, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a reward to the provd, they prate and ſpeak feircely, all the workers of Iniquitie vaunt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but the Lord is my refuge, and my God is the rock of mine hope, and he vvill recompence them in their vvickedneſse, and deſtroy them in their ovvn malice, Yea the Lord our God ſhall deſtroy them. AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>God ſave King James the II.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151739:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
